Emerald Trejo

Fremont, CA 94555 | 619.456.7802 | trejo.emerald.c@gmail.com | Bilingual - Spanish | Military Spouse www.linkedin.com/in/emerald-trejo https://github.com/emeraldtrejo

Software Developer

Experienced in object-oriented programming; developing, testing and debugging code; designing interfaces; and administering systems and networks. A passionate coder, fantastic troubleshooter, and enthusiastic Software Developer who has a long record of developing, implementing and testing software to meet specific project requirements. Sound fundamentals in algorithm design, problem solving and complexity analysis. Demonstrated teamwork and collaboration as well as creative and independent thinker. Highly detail oriented and effective software engineer with a record of exceeding expectations and demonstrating exceptional collaboration and participative problem solving skills.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages: Golang, Python, Java, Bash, C#, C++, JavaScript, Free-Form RPG, HTML/CSS, SQL Frameworks: Vue, .Net, BootStrap, jQuery

Technologies: Git, MobaXterm, Slack Workspace, Apache Directory Studio LDAP Browser, Jira, Confluence, Anaconda, Splunk, Visual Studio Code, Visual Studio (.NET), Agile Development, Eclipse, IntelliJ, AS400, WebSmart, Azure, SuperQuaiL, Trello, Debugging in Google Chrome, Microsoft Office Suite - Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Github, Arcad for DevOps

QUALIFICATIONS

- Masters in Computer Science with emphasis in Software Engineering
- Skilled in all aspects of software project life cycle: feasibility, requirements, design, implementation, integration, test and deployment
- Experience with web development technologies such as JavaScript, HTML, CSS/Bootstrap
- Knowledge of Oracle, MySQL and SQL Server and developing SQL Scripts
- Experience developing object-oriented data driven applications in Windows Environment
- Experience with Full Stack DevOps
- Knowledge of IT Agile Development Practices, Participated in Sprints and User Stories

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Technical Program Manager Intern | Oracle

March 2020 - May 2020

- Add Public and Licensed datasets approved through the legal department to upload into a secure data repository.
- Write scripts in Bash to unzip and upload from desktop to secure data repository
- Manage user stories in Jira to follow requests timeline, document work and uploads
- Submit correspondence inquiries to clients for public datasets when datasets were not readily available for download
- Decommission datasets that were not actively being used in accordance to legal requirements
- Working knowledge of Active Directory/LDAP and identity management systems
- Write scripts to install applications on VM, change access to user, and create files and directories
- Design and develop a python program to scrape 150,000 public datasets from a government research website. Automated program to page through 7952 web pages and download all file extensions to a server and convert HTML links to a string format to save in an array for research references.

Impact of internship: Assist in retrieving data sets used by data scientists to analyze algorithms for advancement of the development of Machine Learning Algorithms. Data retrieved used for advancement of speech recognition across multiple languages, map on word sequences, reading verbal transcriptions for best analysis. Data aiding the training and language model.

Software Developer | Guild Mortgage

June 2019 - February 2020

- Plan and develop in-house software applications through continuous integration and Quality Assurance testing prior to deployment.
- Perform user acceptance and functional testing for deployment and installation of the companywide site.
- Collaborate in an Agile team environment and communicate positively with team members, peers, Business Analysts and Project Managers to capture the impact of changes on applications, systems, and databases and solve complex problems.
- Developed and converted a 3 step process to 1 to facilitate user interface interactivity. The enhancement improved accessibility, productivity, and enabled seamless customer service for users company wide.
- Collaborate on an Agile team to develop a new program to appear for granted employees to enter language preference for borrowers. Produce SQL scripts to dynamically pull data to display and ingest data into a new table
- Develop loan documents in compliance with assigned States loan regulations. Create scripts to pull dynamic data from secure system
- Develop company wide webpage for specific loan program. Webpage derived from conditionals of loan with use of HTML/CSS, Javascript, jQuery and SQL
- Cross join multiple tables using SQL to produce reports from Business Analysts

Data Entry Operator, Government Contractor | Haven 365 LLC

December 2017 - September 2018

- Participated in a Department of Veterans Affairs Pilot program to effectively streamline the processing of invoices to allow Veterans in Chapter 33 vocational rehab program go to school or training
- Processed and submitted for payment 8,500 invoices in a 9 month period with less than 1% error rate
- Effectively performed and analyzed invoices for quality control to abide by US Government requirements for submittal of payment
- Strategized with government officials to implement more effective processes to avoid future backlog of invoices

Romance Travel Specialist | Cruise Planners, American Express Franchise

February 2014 - May 2018

- Managed multiple wedding groups from 20 to 100 people per group to travel abroad while strategically investigating the best price available for clients for their trips.
- Performed quality control checks on sensitive data and managed finances for guests attending the wedding.
- Participate in multiple trade shows to draw new leads and opportunities

EDUCATION

Masters of Computer Science, National University

November 2015 - August 2018

Thesis: Developing an Approximate Heuristic Algorithm based on Existing Exact String Matching Algorithms

Designed a user friendly interface, developing and implementing testable code written in C# on Microsoft Visual Studio platform. Developed a heuristic approximate matching algorithm for genomic sequences based on existing exact pattern matching algorithms. The heuristic approximate algorithm allowed for 50% or greater matches of the pattern against a randomly generated string sequence up to 10,000 characters. The results were then published back to the user. Thesis was compared and analyzed to the Big O Analysis which was used to evaluate the time complexity. Graduate thesis was troubleshooted for defects in the code over the capstone period of 3 months.

Bachelors of Science Psychology, University of California San Diego

Google IT Support Professional Certificate via Coursera

California State University San Marcos Extension: Oracle SQL and PL/SQL + Python Developer + Java Programmer Google IT Automation with Python Certificate via Coursera

Splunk 7x Fundamentals certificate via Splunk

NSE 1 & NSE 2 Network Security Associate Certificate via Fortinet

Programming with Google Go via Coursera

Using Python to Interact with Operating Systems via Coursera

Functions, Methods and Interfaces in Go via Coursera